<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse tending to prove the baptisme in, or under the defection of Antichrist to be the ordinance of Jesus Christ. As also that the baptisme of infants or children is warrantable, and agreeable to the word of God. Where the perpetuity of the estate of Christs Church in the world, and the everlastingnesse of the covenant of Almighty God to Abraham are set forth as maine grounds, and sundry other particular things are controverted and discussed. By P.B.</title>
            <author>Barbon, Praisegod, 1596?-1679.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1642</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78133</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E138_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7333</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99873113</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99873113</idno>
            <idno type="VID">156525</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78133)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 156525)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 25:E138[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse tending to prove the baptisme in, or under the defection of Antichrist to be the ordinance of Jesus Christ. As also that the baptisme of infants or children is warrantable, and agreeable to the word of God. Where the perpetuity of the estate of Christs Church in the world, and the everlastingnesse of the covenant of Almighty God to Abraham are set forth as maine grounds, and sundry other particular things are controverted and discussed. By P.B.</title>
                  <author>Barbon, Praisegod, 1596?-1679.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by R. Oulton &amp; G. Dexter, and are to be sold by Benjamine Allen over against the signe of the Angell in Popes-head Ally,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1642.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>P.B. = Praisegod Barbon.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy following "By P.B." in title: "arbone leather seller in fleetstreet".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:156525:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DISCOURSE <hi>TENDING</hi> TO PROVE THE BAPTISME IN, OR UNDER The Defection of ANTICHRIST to be the Ordinance of <hi>Jeſus Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>AS ALSO That the Baptiſme of Infants or Children is warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and agreeable to the word of GOD.</p>
            <p>Where the perpetuity of the eſtate of <hi>Chriſts Church</hi> in the world, and the everlaſtingneſſe of the Covenant of Almighty GOD to <hi>Abraham</hi> are ſet forth as maine Grounds, and ſundry other particular things are controverted and diſcuſſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By P. B.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Stand in the way, aske for the old way which is the good way, walke therein, and you ſhall finde reſt to your Soules.</hi> 
               <bibl>Jer. 6. 16.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>If it be of</hi> God, <hi>yee cannot deſtroy it, leſt you become fighters againſt</hi> God. <bibl>Acts 5. 38.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <hi>Stand faſt Brethren, and keepe the Ordinances or Traditions you have bin taught by word or by Epiſtle.</hi> 
               <bibl>2 Theſ. 2. 15.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>R Oulton</hi> &amp; <hi>G. Dexter,</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Benjamine Allen</hi> over againſt the ſigne of the <hi>Angell</hi> in <hi>Popes-head Ally,</hi> 1642.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:156525:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:156525:2"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle to the <hi>READER,</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous <hi>READER,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T ſeemeth to be the worke of this preſent age, to be upon the meaſuring of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the Altar, <hi>and them that worſhip</hi> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. 1.</note> 
               <hi>therin;</hi> about the meaſuring of which things, though the truth and true mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure be but one, yet the perſons meaſuring, are very various, and much differing, not only concerning the right underſtanding of the meaſure, but alſo concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the things meaſured: hence it is that diverſitie of opinions and practiſes are found amongſt perſons concerning matt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Godlineſſe,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt which, the matter of this Diſcourſe is not the leaſt, but rather ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the greateſt differences in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Religion, ſo as it, both on the one ſide and on the other, is as a Foundation to be built upon, in regard of many things, which muſt needs follow, according as perſons ſhall hold and beleeve one way or other; and ſo great a difference and diſtance doth it lead men into,
<pb facs="tcp:156525:3"/> that it admitteth of no healing, for till men be agreed about the matter of a thing (that being firſt eſſentiall) how ſhould they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſsibly agree about the thing it ſelfe. The things held forth and maintained, to wit, the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme under the defection</hi> to be the Ordinance of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and the Baptiſme of the ſeed of Beleevers to be Gods will and appointment, as alſo the things oppoſed, namely rebaptizing, or the new way of Baptiſme taken up by ſome, and the refuſing, or denying the Baptiſme of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, are in this Diſcourſe argued and diſcuſſed, not by way of Schoole learning, but by plaine inferences, and ſuch neceſſary conſequences as are not to be denyed. The oppoſite part, in regard of this Diſcourſe, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called, by a Nic-name put upon them, <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts,</hi> ſome of which, are my loving friends and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, whom I would not diſpleaſe, but rather pleaſe, whom I envy not, but love, but the truth is to be loved above all, being moſt deare and precious. Indeed theſe ſeeme to have the zeale of <hi>GOD,</hi> if it were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to right knowledge: they ſeeke after truth, and thinke they have found it, when they imbrace an error, which the further they goe on in, the further out of the way, which appeareth in that ſumme, they miſſe it only in the point of <hi>Baptiſme, &amp;c.</hi> whereas others, (as by an Honourable Perſon was lately obſerved) erre in points of an higher Nature, as namely in holding <hi>Free-will,</hi> fall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng from <hi>Grace, conditionall Election,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:156525:3"/> and denying <hi>Originall ſinne,</hi> opinions accounted as de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to the truth by the Godly. Indeed I have had great reaſoning within me, whether I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceale this Diſcourſe, and keepe it for private uſe, or make it publike, but minding what great diſtraction of minde, and unſetledneſſe doe attend not a few a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout this matter, and minding that ſome of the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed doe give in no further concerning <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants or Children, then as a Tradition of long and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient uſe, whereby many take occaſion to ſtrengthen themſelves, and to confirme others againſt the <hi>Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing</hi> of Children: I have adventured for the truths ſake, to make this common, hoping it may tend to ſome ſatisfaction and ſtay of mens mindes in this matter, and the truth and true ground of things may be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter wayed, and the truth ſome way furthered, and ſome perſons kept from ſuch wonderfull changes and rechanges as are found with them. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie or oneneſſe of minde among the Godly is an excellent thing, and greatly to be deſired, ſo it be in the truth, but <hi>GOD</hi> that of his Infinite wiſdome cauſeth good to come out of evill, cauſeth much profit to attend the variations of his Servants, the truth is the more ſought into and diſcovered, and cometh to ſhine forth more fully after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, <hi>The Children of the truth come to be approved,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Co.</hi> 11. 19.</note> ſo as the matter being ſo unavoydable, in aſmuch as the Scripture muſt needs be true, and every part there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:156525:4"/> fulfilled. It were much to be deſired, that perſons would not be ſo much offended about the differences and variation that are in the matters of Religion and the ſervice of <hi>GOD,</hi> if they would conſider, that great darkneſſe had for a long time attended the world, by the prevailing of the man of ſinne, ſo as men coming out into the light, <hi>ſee men like trees</hi> as the Proverb is: And againe would minde, how great oneneſſe and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment there is in thoſe that d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer, agreeing in the maine points of Beliefe of one <hi>GOD,</hi> one <hi>Lord Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> touching his Natures and Offices; as alſo in the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of <hi>Iuſtification, Redemption, Sanctification,</hi> in the Doctrine of <hi>Free-grace,</hi> and perſeverance therein and many more, too large to be rehearſed here: And then on the otherſide would conſider, how that the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces among the Godly, are of inferior kinde, being only for the moſt part about outward worſhip, and the right way of ſerving <hi>GOD,</hi> wherein if any doe erre, <hi>he falleth to his own Maſter,</hi> and his error cannot reach an other <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ro</hi> 14 4.</note> in way of prejudice or hurt, every one being to give an account unto <hi>GOD</hi> for himſelfe: I ſay if perſons did but minde ſuch like things, it would greatly abate of the prejudice that many have in their mindes, touching this matter, and it would take-off the offence of others, which without ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe they have taken againſt ſuch as ſeeke after the truth by reaſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this; for indeed it muſt needs be a great weakneſſe of minde and want
<pb facs="tcp:156525:4"/> of judgement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be ſo highly diſpleaſed, as ſom are, with varietie of judgements among men, in matters of Religion: And however it is moſt certaine, that it is better there ſhould be differences among men, then that groſſe ignorance ſhould take place, or Papa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny beare ſway and rule as it hath done, and yet doth too much in the world, and the ſame perſons that are ſo offended about differences of opinions, take little or noe offence at the ſame. In reading of this following Diſcourſe I ſhal deſire of thee Courteous <hi>Reader,</hi> who e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thou be, that thou wouldeſt not gather any ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion, as if I held the Church of Rome a tru Church, for indeed I am farre from any ſuch thoughts, holding that State to be the Mother of Fornications, the great where <hi>Sodom</hi> &amp; <hi>Egypt</hi> ſpiritually, according to the account of the Scripture. Now for this Diſcourſe ſent forth, if it ſhall come into the hands of the Learned, I deſire they would take no exception at any <hi>Tottologie</hi> or want of Art they ſhall finde in it, for the Author profeſſeth it not, and did applie himſelfe to weaker capacities, and ſo went over things the ofter that they might the leſſe miſtake or miſ-conſtrue his meaning. If it ſhall come into the hands of thoſe that minde the things as truths, which this Diſcourſe oppoſeth, I pray them to conſider the whole, and one thing with another, before they give judgement; and if it ſhall pleaſe any to make Anſwere, (whereat I ſhall be nothing offended) I deſire
<pb facs="tcp:156525:5"/> they would pleaſe to meaſure ſuch meaſure as I have meaſured to them, whom I truſt I have not in the leaſt wronged; And if in Anſwere they can diſcover any error, I ſhall be content to loſe, ſo the truth may gaine. If any ſhall meet with this that are like to <hi>Gallio,</hi> I only counſell them not to increaſe their bonds by mocking; <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 17.</note> and if they will not be warned, let them mock on. If any moderate and indifferent affected ſhall read this Diſcourſe, and gaine any knowledge by it, let them give the praiſe to <hi>God.</hi> And ſo forbearing to trouble thee Courteous <hi>Reader,</hi> with any thing further, I leave thee to the peruſing of it, (and the bleſsing of <hi>God</hi> to cauſe thee to profit) and reſt,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the ſervice of Love,</hi> P. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:156525:5"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE TENDING TO PROVE the <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> in the defection of Antichriſt, to be the Ordinance of JESUS CHRIST.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE holy Scriptures doe very fully and clearly hold forth the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity and continuation of the eſtate of the viſible or externall Church of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the world, a plant of his own planting not to be rooted out for ever. This having conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> from <hi>Moſes</hi> to our Lord <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and from Him to continue till he ſhall come and deliver it up to his Father, that <hi>God may be all in all.</hi> The perpetuitie and abidingneſſe of <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.</note> this laſt period of the Church under the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, it was foretold by Propheſie, <hi>Eſay</hi> 9. 7. 59. 21. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. witneſſed very fully, <hi>Luke</hi> 1. 33. <hi>Acts</hi> 5. 29. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 29. and it is confirmed by Promiſe, in the 16. <hi>Math.</hi> 18. 28. 20. theſe promiſes (as all other) <hi>are yea and Amen,</hi> ſtable and true for ever, and ſo to be accounted by all the Saints.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:156525:6"/>
            <p> To all which places that give in witneſſe to this we might adde that in the 13. <hi>Hebr.</hi> 8. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever,</hi> as in other conſiderations; ſo the Head, and Husband of his Church his Spouſe, his Body.</p>
            <p>Certainly <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> was never a Widower or Head, without a body, be that farre from any to think, which ſhould be if (at any time) his Church ſeaſed to be, or died out of the world.</p>
            <p>This eſtate of <hi>Chriſts</hi> viſible Church being thus to abide, and abiding and continuing in the world, It hath abode and continued under the defection of Antichriſts uſurpation; or otherwiſe it hath abode and continued ſomwhere elſe in the world, as from under that defection, for ſome where remaining, it muſt be of neceſſity.</p>
            <p>The defection and falling away under Antichriſt was very generall and marvelous univerſall, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by what is written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. 8. 16. And un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the defection had bin ſo, how ſhould thoſe be the <hi>firſt fruits unto God,</hi> that firſt appeared in the dawne of the day (commonly accounted, and that not untruly, as I judge the Waldenſes) if there had bin any that had remained pure and undefiled, as in a Church way. Indeed the Greeks did not alwayes ſubject to the Roman power, yet were very little ſhort in defection. I ſuppoſe according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure whereby the Romaniſt in defection are mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, they will ſtand or fall together. Truly it will be a piece of ſpeciall ſervice to the godly, and very thankfully accepted, if any could make it appeare, ſuch a continuance of the Church eſtate elſewhere
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:156525:6"/> in the world, then (as aforeſaid) it would tend to the ſettling of things very much: and for my part, I ſhould bleſſe <hi>God</hi> for their diſcovery. If none be foundable to make it appeare, as to have continued elſewhere (as I beleeve they cannot) then it wilbe more then probable, that it hath continued under the defection of Antichriſt, according to that of the 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4. for ſome way, and ſome where it muſt continue. And as the Church that great Inſtituted Ordinance is to continue, and hath continued, ſo likewiſe the Ordinance of Baptiſme, by which the matter of the Church is differenced.</p>
            <p>Now if what is before ſaid concerning the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuity of the viſible Church, ſhall be found a truth, and ſo eſteemed, then that muſt needs be found an errour, and ſo accounted, that ſuppoſeth or taketh that for a ground, which is the direct contrary, and flat deniall of this truth, to wit, That the Church hath leaſed at ſome time, and bin utterly extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſht, and <hi>Chriſt</hi> a Widdower for a good ſeaſon, till by themſelves, or ſome others it was revived, and ſo came to live againe: Such as take this for a ground of their practiſe, they muſt needs erre, and build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſands.</p>
            <p>But the way of new Baptizing, la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ely began to be practiſed by ſome, ſuppoſing themſelves, and ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, not to have bin Baptized with the Baptiſme of <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> hath no grou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s practiſe, but the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the Church, and Baptiſme with it, as not remaining in the world. That they are utterly ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed where Antichriſt prevail<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d to exalt himſelfe, their practiſe doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ully declare: and that it is ſo,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156525:7"/> they take for granted and indeed; ſo had they need, for to prove it they cannot; let that be minded, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. 4. <hi>Math.</hi> 16. 18. If it were ſo, that under the defection, the Ordinance of the Church, and Baptiſme ceaſed; yet that it no where remayneth in the world, may not be thought for the reverence of <hi>Gods</hi> Word before declared. But till this alſo be beleeved that the eſtate of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, by which the matter is differenced, is no where elſe to be found, remaining in the world: there is no ground for this practiſe of raiſing Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, by perſons Baptizing themſelves: But rather there would be a ſeeking out the Church, where ſhe were to be found, and there receiving the holy Ordinance of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Baptiſme, as in a right line, and ſo be added to the Church, and from thence conveying the truth into theſe parts againe, where <note place="margin">Acts 2. 47. Pſalm 133.</note> it had ceaſed. <hi>In Sion</hi> of old <hi>God appointed the bleſſing, and life for ever,</hi> and thither, from the utmoſt parts of the earth the godly repair'd, as they very well know. But they doe not beleeve ſuch a continuation, it is plain, and how ſhall they then ſeek there to light their Candle? they muſt ſeek, as they doe, to doe it ſome other way. To help their belief, or make it greater unbelief, I pray them to ſtudie that place, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 8. and ſee how they can reſolve the caſe, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould not have bin a Widower, and a Head without a Body: if his viſible Church had dyed, and left the world, till they, or other, a little ſooner, came and made him one againe, without his ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointing, or leave, or conſent asked; a very mean opinion, unworthy our Lord, or any of his follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers.
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156525:7"/> And whether he will accept of this Spouſe they make him, or reject her as a Harlot, may well be queſtioned; and the rather, ſeeing they have que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned it themſelves once and the ſecond time.</p>
            <p>But I well know ſome are ſo filled with preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, that they have no patience to heare, or ſo much as to think of this matter of the Church eſtate re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining under Antichriſts exaltation: I doe pray them ſetting aſide prejudice, they would be pleaſed to aſſigne and ſet forth the error or abſurdity, the hurt or dammage that cometh of ſuch an opinion, that the Ordinance of the Church, and Baptiſme, have bin in Captivity in Babylon, and there preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the power of <hi>God</hi> for a time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and now by the ſame power brought out and reſtored to free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and purity, <hi>God</hi> returning to build againe his <note place="margin">Acts 15.</note> Tabernacle, bro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e down and ruined, but not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as ſomtime of old the Church and Veſſells of the <hi>Lord</hi> were in Babylon, and from thence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned. When it ſhall pleaſe any to ſet down the <note place="margin">Eſa. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 7. 8. 9. -11.</note> error, or hurt, or dammage, I doe promiſe with <hi>Gods</hi> leave, to conſider of it, and happily it may a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ter my belief in this poynt.</p>
            <p>But now further Baptiſme being loſt and fallen out of the world and an Idoll, and likeneſſe come in the roome of it, the Church being ceaſed, to whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> gave his power; perſons not having the Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> but being unbaptized, all which the opinion and practiſe of New beginning Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme ſuppoſeth to be moſt true and certain, and thereupon doe ground their proceedings.</p>
            <p>I inferre hereupon, that it is, and ever ſhall be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:156525:8"/> found unlawful<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and without warr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt for any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or perſons whatſoever, to attempt, or goe about the raiſing, erecting, or ſetting up of it againe, unleſſe <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 3. 3. 17. 11. 13. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 9. 12.</note> the ſaid perſons have a ſpeciall and particular war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from heaven, and a Commiſſion, as <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> had. The Jewes (though blind could ſee this, that none but a <hi>Chriſt,</hi> a <hi>Moſes,</hi> or <hi>Elias,</hi> or a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet from heaven might doe this; ſo as there being <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1 15</note> no ſuch to be found to reſtore, and newly to erect this Ordinance fallen out of the world, for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to goe about the raiſing of it (as ſome pleaſe to term it) they ſhall but raiſe it from beneath (if not out of the bottomleſſe pit) Commiſſion being want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the actors of it, it ſhal be but only earthly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd from beneath. And it being asked of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, as the <note place="margin">Jo. 3 31.</note> Jewes asked of <hi>John</hi> his Baptiſme, <hi>whether it were from heaven, or of men?</hi> It muſt needs be anſwered of Men, for no Commiſſion can any ſhew to raiſe Baptiſme thus fallen out of the world; nor to Baptiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <note place="margin">Mark. 21. 25</note> or others, being themſelves unbaptized, no more then <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu</hi> could ſhew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or taking other Fire, <hi>Levi.</hi> 10. or <hi>Saul</hi> for ſacrificing in <hi>Samu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi>'s <note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 8</note> abſence. If theſe ſhould be asked as were thoſe that would caſt our Devil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>Jeſus</hi> name, without, Commiſſion, <hi>Ieſus we acknowledge, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aul we know but who are ye?</hi> whence came you? who gave you <note place="margin">Acts 19. 15.</note> Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>miſſion? they muſt need remaine ſilent. Wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is unavoidable in this caſe, till our Lord come, or ſend ſome one from heaven to reſtore, and newly to begin this loſt Ordi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance: for, to doe otherwiſe, <note place="margin">2 Chron. 26. 18, 19.</note> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> as King <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>zia</hi> did, or as did <hi>Saul</hi> in offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ng ſacr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fice in <hi>Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>el</hi>'s abſence, he conceiving
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:156525:8"/> himſelfe to be in a great ſtreight, as indeed they are, and may well take themſelvs to be, that are of ſuch opinion that Baptiſme is loſt, and fallen out of the world, and muſt be by them, as of neceſſitie, be gone againe and reſtored.</p>
            <p>This their attempt it is marvellous that they have not patience and do not waite, ſeeing they, or at leaſt ſome of them, beleeve and expect our Lord <hi>Chriſt</hi> perſonally to appeare againe in the world; happily he may be angry at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir ſudden attempt, that they did not waite and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his coming, or at leaſt, till he had ſent the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſpeciall Commiſſion as he did <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> to prepare his way before him.</p>
            <p>Now if any either have, or ſha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l adventure to be <note place="margin">I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r 23. 21.</note> ſo hardy and venturous, as to run no being ſent, as of old ſome Prophets did, and ſhall ſet about the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this, without Commiſſion and ſpeciall war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, they ſhall but produce and bring forth an Idoll or their own begetting which ſhall be no Ordinance of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> at all; error according to their owne ground, having deſtroyed and made voyd their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Baptiſme, a little error ſhall make voyd this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo: and they ſhall ſtill remaine without the true Baptiſme of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as default in the ſubject made voyde th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ir former Baptiſme, and made them reject it as an Idoll; default in power, and want of a right Inſtrument that hath Authority, ſhall make this to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d alſo, and an Idoll likewiſe, worthy to be rejected: for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a man can receive nothing, <note place="margin">Ioh. 3. 27. Iam 1.</note> unleſſe it be given him from above, and if every good gift be from above, from the Father of lights;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:156525:9"/> This not having Divine Authority in the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo is not from above, from Heaven, as <hi>Johns Baptiſme was,</hi> but from beneath of men earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of no value at all; If default in the ſubject make a nullitie; an Infant of a Beleever, inſtead of a perſon of yeares, profeſſing Faith and Repentance, ſo is their opinion; then in like manner it muſt needs be, that default in power, and want of a Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth make voyd alſo: That is, when an unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed perſon inſtead of a Baptiſed, doth act it. The Commiſſion in the 28 <hi>Matt.</hi> 19. it is moſt plaine, it is to none but to ſuch as were Baptiſed, receiving it from <hi>Iohn</hi> that had Commiſſion to do it, and ſo as in a right line.</p>
            <p>An Unbaptiſed perſon, what hath he to doe with it, or the acting of it? he may be ſure God never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired it at his hands: what warrant hath any Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſed <note place="margin">Eſa. 1. 12.</note> perſon to Baptiſe himſelfe? he may be ſure God never ſpake one word to him about it; as for <note place="margin">Jer. 7. 22.</note> example, there is none in this kinde to be found, not one in all the Scriptures; and truly, for a man to Baptiſe himſelfe, and ſo to begin Baptiſme, (which he muſt neceſſarily thinke is not remaining in the world as before) is ſo ſingular a courſe, and ſo differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from the way and practiſe of the Saints, that it diſcovereth it ſelfe to be erroneous and not of God: The people went to <hi>John</hi> that had Commiſſion, <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Ananias, Cornelius</hi> to <hi>Peter,</hi> the <hi>Eunuch</hi> to <hi>Philip, Diſciples</hi> to ſuch as were <hi>Diſciples</hi> before <note place="margin">Mar. 1. 9.</note> them; yea, our Lord himſelfe, the King of the <hi>Church,</hi> he went to <hi>Iohn:</hi> If any might take liberty to himſelfe, ſure he might, but he minded the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling <note place="margin">Mar. 3. 19.</note>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:156525:9"/> of righteouſneſſe, which how theſe regard it, I leave it to be judged by their practiſe, who will thus adventure to do as never any did before, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Baptiſe themſelves, and then others, when as Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed perſons are in the world, which they will not repaire unto as our Lord did to <hi>Iohn:</hi> If they had queſtioned, as I have heard ſome, going over the Sea, they may pleaſe to minde the example of our Lord, that went over <hi>Iordan</hi> to <hi>Iohn,</hi> but it is likely, they queſtion their Baptiſme that went before them, whether it were true or no, it not being lineally deſcended, and indeed ſo have they cauſe; In like manner others do, and well may queſtion theirs, as feari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g it is but ſome Idoll of their owne, as before is ſaid.</p>
            <p>But all that can be ſaid availeth not to ſatisfie ſome, for by no meanes can they ſee how Baptiſme ſhould be Gods Ordinance, under the defection of Antichriſt. I anſwere, it may well be ſo that they cannot ſee this, nor yet that to be the Temple of God where Antichriſt ſitteth. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 2. this is a great difficulty to many, but what then? may it not be a truth, and ſo indeed in the one and in the other, becauſe many cannot ſee it: yes certainly, unleſſe ſuch as cannot ſee it, had or might be thought to have infallible knowledge and underſtanding: <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>codemus</hi> could not ſee into the truth of the Doctrine <note place="margin">John 3.</note> of Regeneration, or the new birth: our Lord tould him of, yet it was a truth; and ſo is this of Baptiſme being Gods Ordinance, in or under the defection of Antichriſt, though ſome do not, and others cannot ſee it ſo to be: let ſuch minde that this is a myſtery,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:156525:10"/> yea myſteries ſtanding together, the myſterie of the Church, and the myſterie of Iniquitie; theſe being found ſtanding together, no marvaile if they be not ſo eaſily perceived particularly, eſpecially when perſons looke ſo fiercely upon the one, that they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together looſe the ſight of the other, and cannot ſee it, and ſo ſay as <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> how can it be? To be able to diſtinguiſh aright of things, ſtanding th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> together, namely Gods poſts from mens, and mens from Gods, is a point of great wiſdome, which the Lord give men underſtanding to doe aright.</p>
            <p>Oh but the Baptiſme of Infants or Children is ſuch a matter as ſpoyleth all, and maketh voyd Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme forthwith, where it is practiſed, ſo as ever ſince this came into uſe or practiſe in the world. Baptiſme hath there and then ceaſed ſo, as to be non of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Indeed, if it doe make it voyd now, it did ſo at the firſt, and ſo it began to ceaſe, and there was a nullity of the Baptiſme of many before <hi>Chriſt</hi> died, or at leaſt before the Apoſtles left the world, for ought any are able to manifeſt to the contrary, I may ſafely affirme.</p>
            <p>But touching the Baptiſme of Children or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants, if it were an error as ſome ſuppoſe, and would have it; doth it then follow that it is a nullitie, and ſo voyd, becauſe an error is in it? if it were ſo, then is their Baptiſme, their Church, and all their acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, nullities and voyd, having error attending them, as they will confeſſe and muſt doe, unleſſe they will pleade perfection in their courſes, which I truſt they will not doe: ſo as now the queſtion wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l not bee concerning error, but concerning the nature and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:156525:10"/> degree of error which conduceth to make voyd a matter, and ſo this of Baptiſme, and with reference to the quality and degree of error; it is evident, that as great error attends their new Baptiſme, as the Baptiſme of Infants, or theirs in infancie: let the matter of the eſtate of defection be added to it; So as here is no ground to goe upon, but that which leadeth into an endleſſe Labyrinth: and indeed, this ſome of them have come to ſee and to confeſſe, and ſo have rejected their ſecond Baptiſme alſo, and taken up a third, which in time no doubt, when their heate is over, and they have more ſeriouſly conſidered of it, they will ſee it to be as faulty as their firſt or ſecond, and that it is to be rejected alſo.</p>
            <p>But if an error doe not make a nullitie, as it is moſt ſure it doth not, no though the error ſhould be great, then may the Baptiſme in and under the defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, be and remaine Gods Ordinance, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding all the error or errors that attend it, or are in it: And indeed ſo it doth, ſo as there is no need of this new way never heard of in the word of <hi>God,</hi> namely of a perſons Baptiſing of himſelfe, and ſo others afterward, or others before he himſelfe being Unbaptiſed, when as they ſayd, perſons were before partakers of the true Baptiſme of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> notwithſtanding there were ſome errors attending the adminiſtring of it to them; for all that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes will beare, or can be gathered in this matter concerning the ſubject, is but at the moſt, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſhould keepe back their Infants or Children from the Ordinance, leaſt they happily ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:156525:11"/> the ſame by overtimely uſing and partaking of it, and ſo tarrying till nature had given ſome ripe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in ſpeech and utterance, and art by Induſtry in way of Education had done its part alſo, before ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven yeares they might become capable ſubjects, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to theſe mens ground, confeſſing Faith, and profeſſing Repentance, when they have never a whit more grace then the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had the firſt day they came into the world, and in this way as I am infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſome in the <hi>Nether-lands</hi> are fully pleaſed and contented; a very empty buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>But now very lately ſome are mightily taken, as having found out a new defect in the <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> under the defection, which maketh ſuch a nullitie of <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme,</hi> in their conceit, that it is none at all, and it is concerning the manner of <hi>Baptizing,</hi> wherein they have eſpyed ſuch default, as it maketh an abſolute nullity of all perſons <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> but ſuch as have bin ſo <hi>Baptized,</hi> according to their new diſcovery; and ſo partly as before, in regard of the ſubject, and partly in regard of ſo great default in the manner: They not only conclude, as is before ſayd, a nullity of their preſent <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> And ſo, but addreſſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be <hi>Baptized</hi> a third time, after the true way and manner they have found out, which they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count a precious truth. The particular of their opinion and practiſe is to Dip, and that perſons are to be Dipped, all and every part to be under the Water; for if all the whole perſon be not under the Water, then they hold they are not <hi>Baptized</hi> with the <hi>Baptiſme</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> As for Sprinkling, or pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Water on the Face, it is nothing at all as they
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:156525:11"/> account, and ſo meaſuring themſelves by theſe new thoughts, as unbaptized, they addreſſe themſelves to take it up after the manner of Dipping: but truly they want a Dipper that hath Authority from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, as had <hi>John,</hi> whom they pleaſe to call a Dipper, of whom it is ſayd, <hi>that it might be manifeſted his Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme was from heaven.</hi> A man can receive nothing, that is, lawfull authority or power to <hi>Baptize,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it be given from heaven, which I deſire they <note place="margin">John 3. 17.</note> would be pleaſed to mind, and they will eaſily ſee their third <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is from the Earth, and not from heaven, as <hi>Iohns</hi> was. And if this caſe be further conſidered, it will appeare at the moſt to be but a defect in the manner, and a coming ſhort in the quantity of the Element. It is a wonderfull thing that a nullity ſhould thereof follow forthwith; of which more may be ſeen in the ſame caſe before. Againe, that the ſubſtance of an Ordinance of ſo high a nature and great concernment, ſhould be founded in the Critickneſſe of a word, and in the quantity of an Element, is no leſſe marveilous to ſay no more. Oh but <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is a Buriall, as it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, <note place="margin">Colo 2. 12.</note> 
               <hi>We are Buried with him in Baptiſme,</hi> &amp;c. and we are raiſed up alſo to newneſſe of life. This Buriall and reſurrection, only Dipping can import and hold forth. Whereunto I ſay it is very true, that <hi>Baptiſme</hi> is a Buriall, and holdeth forth our Buriall and riſing with <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And ſo it is in regard of the perſon that is Baptized by Sprinckling, or powring Water on the Face, as they are pleaſed to ſay, they are under the water, and Buried. I deſire they would ſhew how elſe they were <hi>Baptized</hi> unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:156525:12"/> and in the Sea, when not ſo much as an hair of their <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.</note> heads was wet. But while they force <hi>Baptiſme</hi> to hold forth Buriall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they loſe that which it hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth forth equally with Buriall and Reſurrection, namely the ſprinckling of the Conſcience of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 52 15. Heb. 10. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ezek 36 25 Heb. 12. 24. Act. 23. 16. Heb. 10. 22. 1 Cor 6. 11. Rev 1. 5.</note> in the blood of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> and the laver of Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration, or waſhing in the blood of <hi>Chriſt</hi> that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Fountaine, imparted and held forth by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, as well as Buriall and Reſurrection, which is wholly loſt in this way of inforcing, only Dipping to hold forth Buriall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For all doe, or may know, that a thing Dipped in Water, is not therfore wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed or made clean; neither is waſhing alwayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended in the Dipping of a thing in Water. Indeed waſhing, to make cleane, is by the way of Dipping many times, that by putting the thing into Water, and rubbing of it, or the like, it might be cleanſed, which I conceive it was the way of their waſhing in thoſe times, and Countries, where Baptiſme was firſt begun; as it is the manner now in many caſes, eſpecially where there is much Water, and much filth in the thing waſhed.</p>
            <p>And that it is or may be a laudable way eſpecially in the hot Countries, to dip a part rather then the whole, I will not gaine-ſay, but that waſhing (inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mating waſhing in the blood of CHRIST) is the maine thing held forth in Baptiſme, I ſuppoſe it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be denyed, and that a little water ſufficeth to hold forth aſwell as a great deale, and that to one part (as the face, as the uſuall manner now is) as to the whole: So as he that is waſhed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eeds not but to be waſhed in one part, and is cleane all, according as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:156525:12"/> our Lord tould <hi>Peter</hi> (who it ſeemeth was of the <note place="margin">Joh. 13 9.</note> minde theſe are of) who would have his hands and his head, even as theſe will have the whole, over head and eares, as men uſe to ſay, dipped, but not therefore waſhed as before.</p>
            <p>And furthermore to reſolve and determine how this totall dipping can ſtand with modeſty and ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faſtneſſe, is a hard matter to be made apparant. If out of modeſty perſons ſhall uſe a linnen garment or the like, it will be very conſiderable, whether this is not to be modeſt above what is written: If that ſhall be reſolved, ſure thoſe veſtments muſt needs be very holy veſtments that ſhall be Baptiſed into the death and Reſurrection of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt:</hi> I ſuppoſe they may equallize the Surplice, if not excel it: being the fruit of voluntary Religion, both of them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Romaniſts</hi> ſome of them, and ſome of the poore ignorant <hi>Welch</hi> do uſe dipping, I thinke theſe will not ſay they learned this new truth of them, neither do I thinke they will hold their Baptiſme ever the truer for their dipping: I hope when they have further conſidered this matter, they may abate of the fiercenes of their opinion: ſo as to thinke that Baptiſme under or in the defection may be Gods Ordinance, ſo as there ſhall be no need of this new dipping.</p>
            <p>But in aſmuch as this is a very new way, and the full growth of it, and ſettling is not yet known, if it be to themſelves, yet not to me and others: I will forbeare to ſay further to it.</p>
            <p>And here let me declare how wonderfull ſtrange
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:156525:13"/> the thoughts of men ſeem to me in the minding of the things of <hi>Gods</hi> Ordaining, that if it happen that mens deviſes are added to them, or ſet by them, they conceive them to ceaſe and loſe their being: when as the things of God are more ſtrong and durable, then ſo eaſily to fade and vaniſh: It is moſt certaine that <hi>every plant not planted by God, ſhall be plucked up,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Ma. 15. Act. 5 1 Sam 5. 4.</note> but what is of God cannot ſo eaſily be deſtroyed: <hi>Dagon</hi> may fall before the <hi>Arke,</hi> and be broken to peeces, but the <hi>Arke</hi> be unſhaken, though among the <hi>Philiſtines,</hi> and from thence brought forth againe without any alteration of the nature of it, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Veſſells in like manner brought out of <hi>Babell,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out change of their relation, which thing, if per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons <note place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. 8.</note> would minde, they would expect the ruins of <hi>Babell,</hi> and all mens Inventions, rather then to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of any ſuch conceit of the ruine of Gods waies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the devices of Satan, as if he were ſtronger then God.</p>
            <p>But woting well, that many have a vaine this way, to pull up the Wheate with the Tares, and to <note place="margin">Ma 13. 29. Ezek. 43. 8.</note> deſtroy Gods poſts together with mens, becauſe mens poſts are ſet neere unto them, and unleſſe they doe thus they thinke they do nothing at all, never minding any ſevering or diſtinguiſhing: I will leave the further proſecuting of this laſt trade at the preſent, and ſay ſomething of the fore part, where there is two things conſiderable as generall grounds, in the minding whereof, ſundry particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars will fall in. The firſt is the Covenant of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God to <hi>Abraham</hi> and to his ſeed after him, in their generations. <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7. It is an everlaſting
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:156525:13"/> Covenant, as in the nature of it, ſo in the extent, being made to a thouſand generations, continuing <note place="margin">Pſal. 105. 8</note> to the time of Grace, being in force after the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of our Lord, as apeareth by that of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle; <hi>Yee are the Children of the Prophets, and of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant,</hi> and againe, <hi>the Covenant is made to you and to</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 3. 25. 2. 39.</note> 
               <hi>your Children,</hi> yea it did extend to the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> they were a part of the ſeed unto whom this everlaſting Covenant was made, as we ſhall further ſhew here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. This Covenant of Almighty <hi>God</hi> as it is e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting, and hath the ſame extent for ever, as ever it had; ſo it is a diſtinct thing from either of the Teſtaments, old or new; for let it be minded, there is but two Teſtaments, an old one by <hi>Moſes,</hi> a new <note place="margin">Heb. 8. 6, 7, 8.</note> one by our <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſo the Scripture is cleare, <hi>Hebrews</hi> 8. one confirmed by the blood of Goates, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the other in or by the blood of the Sonne of <hi>God:</hi> Now the Covenant to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed is neither of theſe two; the old it is not, nor any part of it, it was made 430 yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and noe whit diſanulled, ſwallowed up or made voyd by the Teſtament of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as expreſſely the Apoſtle doth witneſſe, 3 <hi>Gala.</hi> 17. the new it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be, in aſmuch as it is, as before is ſhewed, 430. yeares older then the old, and to make it a part of the new as ſome do, is to ſubvert the order of <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, for ſo the new Teſtament by CHRIST the Sonne, ſhould be indeed the old, and the old by <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> 430 yeares after, ſhould be the new: alike mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake it is, to make it a part of the old, or the old it ſelfe, as ſome doe, and ſo to count it legall and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and the like, when as indeed it is moſt gracious and hath nothing but free grace in it, and in all the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:156525:14"/> parts of it, and indeed but for digreſſion from the matter in hand, I would ſay ſomething further about this matter, becauſe I know ſome will count this a new thing, but let them minde, that though a Covenant and Teſtament have a common and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall acceptance in the Scripture phraſe, yet in ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſpeaking they are diſtinct and divers, and not the ſame.</p>
            <p>A Teſtament can be confirmed noe otherwiſe but by death or blood, ſo the Apoſtle, and ſo were <note place="margin">He. 9. 6.</note> both the Teſtaments old and new; but a Covenant is otherwiſe ratified, and a perſon may make divers Covenants, but he can make but one Teſtament, in aſmuch as he can die but once. Almighty GOD made one free gracious and everlaſting Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed, and two Teſtaments as we ſaid before, one by <hi>Moſes</hi> which waxed old, and one new by his Sonne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>Lord:</hi> and though this may ſeeme new, let any in ſoberneſſe ſhew the error that attends it.</p>
            <p>Now to returne to our matter, This Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his ſeed being a diſtinct thing from either of the teſtaments, and being everlaſting, and not made voyd by either of the Teſtaments, the ſeed of the faithfull muſt needs be intereſſed in it ſo long as it doth laſt and continue, but as before it is everlaſting, and ſo in the extent of it, ſo as the belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Gentiles</hi> and their ſeed are intereſſed in it and made <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, they according as the Apoſtle declares in the 3 <hi>Ephe.</hi> 6. are made fellow heires and of the ſame body, and partakers of his promiſe or Covenant in <hi>Chriſt</hi> through the Goſpell: The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe or Covenant in the 17 <hi>Gen.</hi> 7. The <hi>Gentiles</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:156525:14"/> they be a part of the ſeed to whom the promiſe was made. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 16. which was made ſure and good when the partition wall was broken down, and there was neither Jew nor Greeke, &amp;c. but all one in <hi>Chriſt. Abraham</hi> being made according to the <note place="margin">Gal. 3. 28.</note> promiſe of <hi>God,</hi> a Father not of one only, but of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Nations; that ſo in him and in his ſeed, <hi>all the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Earth might be bleſſed,</hi> he being made a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note place="margin">Rom. 4.</note> to them all (not only to the Circumciſion, but to the uncircumciſion) according to the extent of the promiſe, and everlaſting Covenant of Almighty God unto him, in the fulfilling whereof the promiſe was made ſure and good to all the ſeed. <hi>Romans</hi> 4. 16. 17.</p>
            <p>Indeed the <hi>Jewes</hi> as branches of the Stock of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham,</hi> were broken off (yet not all) and the <hi>Gentiles</hi> grafted thereon, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. 17. which was according to that foretold by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> the Kingdome ſhould be taken from them, and given to a people that would bring forth the fruite thereof, namely the <hi>Gentiles Matt.</hi> 21. 43. And ſo thoſe other ſheepe brought in, that were not of that Fold. <hi>Iohn</hi> 10. that there might b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one Shepherd and one Sheepe-fold, and not two: the promiſe it being to ſeed and not to ſeeds; that is, to <hi>Iewes</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> united together in one in <hi>Chriſt. Gala.</hi> 3. 16. from all which, and much more that might be ſaid, I take it to be moſt evident, That the Covenant to <hi>Abraham</hi> was everlaſting, and to continue for ever: that it did extend it ſelfe to the <hi>Gentiles</hi> as it did to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> to the Natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that beleeve, as to the Nation of the <hi>Jewes:</hi> to the ſeed of theſe and their poſteritie now, as to them and their poſteritie of old. That they; to wit,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:156525:15"/> Children of the faithfull, are of the Church of <hi>God,</hi> and within the Covenant to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo by juſt conſequence have a right to ſuch Ordinances as are the ſeale of that Covenant, as of old, namely to be Circumciſed with Circumciſion made without hands, and to be buried with <hi>Chriſt</hi> by Baptiſme: ſo <note place="margin">Colo. 2. 11.</note> as it muſt needs be a great wrong and violence to the Covenant of Almighty <hi>God,</hi> and injury to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Father of the Faithfull, to exclude ſuch as <hi>God</hi> hath not only neceſſarily included, but expreſt in that his everlaſting Covenant, namely the Lineall ſeed of the Faithfull: to forbid ſuch to come to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as ſometime ſome Diſciples did, finding fault <note place="margin">Ma. 19. 13, 14.</note> with them that bring them, as did thoſe, whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> blamed, muſt needs be a changing the everla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting Covenant, and a bringing in a new Goſpell never learned of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Minding that former to be very cleare, that the Covenant is everlaſting, the ſame, of the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent, the lineall ſeed of the faithfull within it: I now proceed to the conſideration of the ſecond thing, which is, That the eſtate of <hi>Chriſts</hi> Church, hath bin, and is ſtable and firm, abiding to perpetui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: ſome change in form and adminiſtration, but not in matter and relation. Proofe of this I ſhall ſpare, having done it before, to which I referre the Reader. Now all doe confeſſe, that Infants or Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren before they came to yeares of underſtanding, were formerly a part of the Church, and true and lawfull Members, from <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> from <hi>Moſes</hi> to <hi>Christ,</hi> what ſhould let them to be a part of the Church yet ſtill, and true and lawfull Members, ſeeing the Church or Kingdome is the ſame, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:156525:15"/> to that of our Lord before declared, <hi>Math.</hi> 21. 43. And ſeeing the Gentiles they are fellow heires, (and but fellow heires) and of the very ſame Body or Church <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 6. how can it be imagined on the part of any ſoberly minding the truth, that Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren or Infants of the Faithfull, ſhould be now ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, touching which GOD hath never ſpoken one word, but the contrary. Sure there is ſomething in the diſtribution which the Apoſtle maketh of the Church, Husbands and Wives, Maſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Parents and Children, yea Children to be e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducated and brought up in the feare of God. What <note place="margin">Ephe. 6. 1 Cor. 11.</note> had he to doe with them, if <hi>without,</hi> as theſe account? And beſide, can any imagine that when the Jewes ſhalbe grafted in againe into their own Olive tree, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. that then their ſeed ſhalbe excluded, and left out, as not any more capable of that grace and favour; ſure this were greatly to leſſen their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and much to diminiſh of the grace of Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh but (ſay ſome) what of all this? if it were ſo, there is no example in the new Teſtament for it?</p>
            <p>Anſwer, no more there is no example for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons Baptizing of himſelfe, or to Baptize others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe unbaptized: let any ſhew the latter; I ſhall undertake when he hath done, to doe the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. But there is precept, or warrant for the latter may ſome ſay, namely, that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. 6. 7. <hi>Say not who ſhall aſcend into heaven,</hi> &amp;c. Surely they are neare driven, that have no other proof but ſuch for their practiſe: <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> might have made uſe of that proof to their purpoſe, and ſo might thoſe many Proſelytes, who from farre Countries
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:156525:16"/> came to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and were added to the Church, they might, if they had bin as wiſe as theſe, have ſtayed at home, and Circumciſed themſelves, and ſo ſerved <hi>God:</hi> for in like manner they were not to ſay, <hi>Who ſhall aſcend into heaven,</hi> the Word it being nigh unto them. But they knew otherwiſe, and ſo may theſe, that are to repaire to the Church, where ſhe is to be found; yea though they ſhould goe as farre as the Eunuch went, to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> or as the Queen of <hi>Sheba,</hi> that came from the utmoſt parts of the earth; <note place="margin">Mat. 12. 43.</note> yea, our Lord might have ſpared the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our of full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> in going over <hi>Jordan</hi> to <hi>John;</hi> he might have ſtayed at home, and Baptized him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, the Word being nigh unto him. But it may be they have ſome other proofe that I doe not know of: indeed ſo have they need, or elſe they are in a poore caſe.</p>
            <p>But a great matter it is with ſome, that <hi>Abraham</hi> had two Sonnes, one borne after the fleſh of <hi>Agar</hi> the Bond-woman, and one borne after the Promiſe, by <hi>Sarah</hi> a Free-woman. This the Apoſtle ſaith is an Allegory, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. In way of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſion to theſe two, the Apoſtle ſaith that <hi>Hieruſalem, that now is, is in Bondage, as was Hagar and her Sonne, but Hieruſalem that is above is free, the Mother of us all:</hi> hence high Notions attend the minds of ſome, and upon this Allegorie not well underſtood, I ſuppoſe they build very ſtrongly, for the rejecting of Children from the Covenant, and putting of them from Baptiſme, the ſeale or ſigne of it; unto which matter I anſwere, and ſay indeed <hi>Abraham</hi> had two Sonnes of two Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> and theſe were Types of two ſtates of people, and did point unto the time of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:156525:16"/> grace, when the truth and ſubſtance of this was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, when <hi>Chriſt</hi> came unto his own, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him not, but to ſuch as did, <hi>he gave power to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Jo. 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>the Sonnes of God,</hi> ſo many as did beleeve in his name; thoſe that did not, as the greateſt number did not, they became bound, as <hi>Hagar</hi> and her Sonne, and ſo was the preſent ſtate of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> but the <hi>Gentiles</hi> beleeving (Children of the promiſe) with a remnant of the <hi>Jewes,</hi> were made free by the Sonne through beleeving, and were the <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> that was from above, the Mother of us all: The <hi>Hebrewes</hi> or <hi>Iewes</hi> were caſt out for unbelief, as the Bond-woman and her Sonne were for mocking, and ſo were in the ſame ſtate, and yet ſtill are, that <hi>Iſmael</hi> and all his poſteritie were: But ſuch as did imbrace the Sonne, and believe, whether <hi>Iewes</hi> or <hi>Gentiles,</hi> were made free by the Sonne that maketh men free indeed. <note place="margin">Jo. 8. 36.</note> And thus that Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>egory is made good, and that Type fulfilled, and we <hi>Gentiles</hi> are as <hi>Iſaac,</hi> Children of <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 31.</note> the promiſe.</p>
            <p>Oh no ſay ſome, Children of the promiſe are true (they meane lively) beleevers, and Children of the fleſh are Infants: this is a marvellous underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing indeed, <hi>Iſaack</hi> lineally deſcending from <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> being an Infant, was the Sonne of promiſe, and ſo were his Lineall ſeed to a thouſand generations, that did proceed from him Lineally; of which Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neall ſeed, ſome were in time, lively beleevers, and ſome carnall and voyd of the Spirit; yet all the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſeed of promiſe.</p>
            <p>I (may ſome ſay) it is true, under that Covenant it was ſo. I anſwere, the Covenant is ſtill the ſame, though the Teſtaments differ, which no way alters
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:156525:17"/> the caſe. I but (ſay ſome) it is ſayd, If we be <hi>Chriſts,</hi> then are we <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I anſwere, it is ſo <note place="margin">Gala. 3. 29.</note> ſayd of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> in oppoſition to the <hi>Iewes:</hi> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> beleeving are <hi>Chriſts</hi> as before, and heires ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to promiſe, and the promiſe is to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents and their ſeed, as to <hi>Iſaack</hi> and his ſeed. Then <hi>Iſmael</hi> might challenge right, might ſome ſay, <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maell</hi> I ſay was noe child of promiſe, and though hee were <hi>Abrahams</hi> Lineall ſeed, hee was caſt out, and ſo were the <hi>Jewes</hi> that rejected <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and ſo ſhall it fare with the <hi>Gentiles</hi> when they will noe longer owne <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> they then ſhall be rejected alſo, and the <hi>Jewes</hi> when they ſhall come to beleeve <note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> ſhall be grafted in againe into their own ſtock and Olive tree. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. A very high myſtery which the Apoſtle would not have men ignorant (to wit us <hi>Gentiles)</hi> of it, that we might feare and not be high-minded: but alas, ſome will be ignorant of it, whether the Apoſtle will or noe, and be high-min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded alſo, and boaſt againſt the branches as carnall: and for lively beleevers, ſuch as theſe men meane; indeed truly, and I conceive not unproperly, they may be called the ſeed of <hi>God,</hi> and his Sonnes being <note place="margin">Jo. 2. 2. chap. 5. 1. Rom. 4.</note> borne of him: and if <hi>Abraham</hi> be honoured by Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty <hi>God</hi> to be called their Father, alſo he being a Father to all that beleeve; he of old, yea alwaies had ſuch among his ſeed, but knowne only to <hi>God,</hi> that only knoweth the heart and knoweth his own. As for theſe what ever they talke, they cannot as of certaine infallibility, ſhew us one of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Children according to this their ſenſe, but they muſt vaile the matter to charity, and if they would pleaſe to extend their charity but a little further,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:156525:17"/> they without any error or abſurdity, may take in Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren alſo.</p>
            <p>There are ſundry other Scriptures controverted about this matter and reaſons, <hi>pro</hi> and <hi>con,</hi> which for brevity ſake I will forbeare, and ſhall only here intimate, how uncom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable a Doctrine this is, of denying the lineall ſeed of the faithfull to be of the Church, and within the Covenant of Almighty God, as of old, for from thence it muſt needs follow, that Parents doe beget, beare, and bring forth Children to the Divell: ſure he is much beholding to them for increaſing his Kingdome, but what ſad thoughts may hereupon attend them, I leave it to them to conſider that are of ſuch beliefe, and propound to them, whether they could not thinke it were as good to burne, as to marry, or at leaſt to be baren, as to be fruitfull and beare Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and do ſuch ſervice to the Divell in the Augmenting his number. But it may be, they will thinke themſelves, that their children have no originall ſinne, and ſo reſolve the caſe juſt as ſome doe.</p>
            <p>Indeed it ſeemeth, that ſuch like ſad and perplexed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ughts or reaſonings ſome of the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily had, whereof they deſired to have reſolution from the Apoſtle, who telleth them, that if one perſon, either Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band or Wife be a Beleever, then were their Children ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note place="margin">1 Cor. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> or ſeparate, otherwiſe they were uncleane or common: This is a very conſiderable matter; ſome knowne thing ſure the Apoſtle alludeth unto, that he ſpeaketh thus: we may take knowledge, that of old the Nation and Church of the <hi>Iewes</hi> was holy and ſeparate, and all Nations and people elſe, were common and uncleane: The ſubſtance of which matter ſtanding good, cauſeth the Apoſtle to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre by way of a reaſon here, <hi>elſe were your Children common or uncleane, but now are they holy or ſeparate.</hi> This reaſon hath little force, or can give ſmall ſatisfaction to the <hi>Corinthia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s,</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:156525:18"/> unleſſe ſome known thing were minded, or underſtood of them. This now is like to be ſomething which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had held forth, which muſt be this, that perſons not of the Church, nor within the Covenant, were common and uncleane. To omit the many places that might be produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced out of the Law, wherein there is much ſtrength, which apeareth by the Apoſtles alleaging the Law in a like caſe; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 13.</note> That in the 10<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of the <hi>Acts</hi> will informe us concerning this very fully, where by a viſion <hi>Peter</hi> was taught, not to call any <hi>common or uncleane,</hi> namely the <hi>Gentiles</hi> that did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve in him: we may ſee what was counted common or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane: in a viſion the creatures of all kindes are ſhewed <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts.</hi> 10.</note> him, and he is bidden to eate, he replieth, he never eate things <hi>common or uncleane:</hi> that which <hi>Peter</hi> was taught by this, followeth, not to count the <hi>Gentiles</hi> beleeving, as common and uncleane, and this appeareth by his under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it. ver. 28. So the other beleevers accounted in like manner, thou wenteſt in to men uncircumciſed, and hadſt fellowſhip with them, which they accounted com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon <note place="margin">chap. 11. 3</note> and uncleane, ſo was the common ſenſe, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, the <hi>Iewes</hi> meddle not with the <hi>Samaritans; Yee know</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>it is an unlawfull thing for a Jew to keepe compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, &amp;c.</hi> but <hi>God</hi> hath ſhewed, that I ſhould not account <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iohn.</hi> 4. 9.</note> any common or uncleane, that is, for his kindred or Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hee meaneth, ſo hee feare God and beleeve, otherwiſe the Scripture teacheth, that the beleever hath no part with the Infidell, but muſt come out and touch no uncleane thing and be ſeparate: Thus is the Apoſtles ſenſe and <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor</hi> 6. 15 17.</note> meaning found out, a common and knowne thing: noe perſon whatſoever fearing <hi>God,</hi> and beleeving, are to be counted common or uncleane; and as not they, ſo not their ſeed or children; yea if but one of them be ſuch, which is a further extending of the grace and favour to them, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragment, with comfort to continue together, their
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:156525:18"/> Children being not uncleane or common, but the children of God, holy and ſeparate, which is the ſecond thing we are to minde, who according to the Scripture account and the reckoning of them, to whom the Scripture did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belong, were eſteemed <hi>holy and ſeparate</hi> of old in the Law, <hi>Deu.</hi> 7. 6. 14. 2. 21. 29. 9. we may plainly ſee, and touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing children in the 9 <hi>Eſra</hi> 2. it is ſayd, <hi>the holy ſeed,</hi> ſo in <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. 24 12. 7. the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> alleadgeth an exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Law to this purpoſe, and applieth it: <hi>Be yee holy, for I the Lord your God am holy,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 16. according to the ſubſtance of the truth known and held forth as before, wee are to minde the Apoſtle here, <hi>now are your Children holy or ſeparate,</hi> and ſo there is great ſatisfaction to the beleeving party, that however their children are the children of God and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oly, whereas but only for them, they were but com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and uncleane: yet now in regard of them, and their being in the Covenant, and of the Church, their Children are accounted as Children both unto God as of old, and holy: as it was ſayd of <hi>Iſrael, the Sons which thou haſt borne unto me.</hi> Thus is this latter ſenſe found out and diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and the meaning of the Apoſtle manifeſted, in way of <note place="margin">Eze. 16. 20.</note> the right of Children to the Covenant, Church eſtate and Ordinances (which they are capable of) holy things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to holy perſons, ſuch are Children, according to the account of the Apoſtle.</p>
            <p>But the opponents of the right of Children to the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, Church, Eſtate, and Ordinances, tell us, and would have us to beleeve them, that by <hi>common or uncleane,</hi> is meant, Baſtardy, or illegitimacie, and ſo they would have the ſenſe thus, elſe were your Children Baſtards or illegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, <hi>but no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> they are holy,</hi> that is, true borne or legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate. Truly this is a wonderfull underſtanding, and that which holds forth no light at all, according to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, to ſatisfie the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> with the Apoſtles reaſon,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:156525:19"/> if one be a beleever, then your Children are true borne, and not Baſtards: I ſay noe more to it, but that ſure it is a Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtardly ſenſe and underſtanding of the Apoſtles reaſon, and that which will make a many Baſtards in the world, and they will hardly exempt themſelves from the number according to their own ground. But they tell us further, that the ſanctitie of the unbeleever to the beleever, is to his lawfull uſe, which is the ſame (ſay they) with the holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the Children: To which I anſwere, it is an eaſy thing to ſay ſo, but a great deale harder to prove it: The Scripture teacheth, <hi>that to the pure all things,</hi> namely lawfull <note place="margin">Tit. 1, 15:</note> things <hi>are pure,</hi> and ſo the wife to the Husband, and the Husband to the wife in Gods Ordinance; but the holyneſſe of the Children is an other thing, according to the reaſon of the Apoſtle before ſet forth, which I deſire may be min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and I ſhall need ſay nothing further: and truly this point of outward or viſible holyneſſe or unholyneſſe of commonneſſe, and being uncleane, is a point of great con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment, which for want of right and due conſideration great miſtakes doe attend perſons, but I may not inlarge to ſpeake of it here.</p>
            <p>But yet ſtill the matter remaineth to be declared, that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo much ſtick at, and that is an example or precept for this practiſe of Baptizing Children, which before I ſpeake unto: I ſhall deſire firſt that they would minde what hath bin ſayd before ſeriouſly and without prejudice. Secondly I deſire they would give ſuch meaſure as they require to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, namely, an example or precept for an Unbaptized perſon to Baptiſe himſelfe or others. Thirdly, I would pray them to conſider, whether they doe not thinke the Apoſtle would have ſpoken more particularly concerning the rejecting of Children, and keeping them off from the Church, the cuſtome being ſo ancient, that Parents with their Children came in together; an example of refuſing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:156525:19"/> them lyeth rather on their part to ſhew. Laſty, I will in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to ſhew them ſome precepts and examples: And firſt for examples: It is evident, Children were Baptized aſwell as men of yeares, unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10. 2. this is a cleare example, and there is more in it then ſome are ware of.</p>
            <p>Secondly, there is cleare examples of Baptizing houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds, the Jaylors and <hi>Lydia,</hi> and the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus</hi> by <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 16. and as theſe, ſo queſtionleſſe other houſholds, as well as thoſe three. It is a rare thing to think there ſhould be no Children. If Children with their Parents were not, as of old, to enter the Covenant, Church-ſtate, and Ordinance of Initiation, <hi>Baptiſme</hi> now as Circumciſion of old, ſurely the Apoſtle would not have ſpoken ſo generally, and eſpecially conſidering the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelytes alway of old brought in their Children with them, as a part of the whole: Yea I affirme it is a full example in force for a preſident to after times, that Families may, and ought to be Baptized; yea whole Families, for <hi>Paul</hi> Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the houſhold of <hi>Stephanus;</hi> and there is no example of putting by Children at all. And I further adde, that if a houſhold, or houſholds ſhould be tendered to Baptiſme, wherein there were Children or Infants, if <hi>Pauls</hi> example, and the other ſhould be alledged for pattern: I ſuppoſe they had need have an example at the leaſt, if not a Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to refuſe the doing of it, unleſſe they would wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fully ſhew they are not the followers of him, as he was of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Co. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0.</note> that would have Children to come unto him, and not to be forbidden, there being no coming to him here, but in his Church, eſpecially when he hath ſayd that of ſuch are his Kingdome.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Children of the Church of <hi>Coloſſ</hi> were Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized as is plaine, the whole Church were buried with <hi>Chriſt</hi> in Baptiſme, as the whole Church of old were Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed;
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:156525:20"/> and as of old, they were Baptized unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> as before. Now a part of the Church were Children, <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſ.</hi> 3. 20, 21.</p>
            <p>But further, there is the plaine order and command of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> for the Baptizing of Children, which I make appeare thus, <hi>Abraham</hi> was to be made according to <hi>Gods</hi> Covenant unto him, a Father of many Nations, and ſo were his ſeed to be: the Jews for a time, were the only people: but the time came, the Kingdome was to be taken from them, and given to a Nation, the Gentiles, that ſhould bring forth the fruit of it. Many Nations are to be <hi>Abrahams,</hi> and to have him for their Father. Now all theſe Nations, according to the expreſſe command of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the 28. <hi>Math.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9. are to be Baptized, and who dare gainſay him? Now however, it is poſſible, though nothing likely, there <note place="margin">
                  <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 4 18.</note> ſhould be three Families, and no Children in them; yet that there ſhould be Nations and no Children, is altogether impoſſible. But the Nation, and all Nations that imbrace <hi>Chriſt,</hi> are to be Baptized, according to <hi>Chriſts</hi> command, and ſo Children as a party, even as of old, they were a part of the Nation of the Jewes, and Circumciſed, yea and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized unto <hi>Moſes</hi> as before. The Nations that are made <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed; the Nations that are ſaved; the Kingdomes which ſhall become the Kingdomes of our Lord, muſt needs receive <hi>Chriſts</hi> badge, and be Baptized according to <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 24.</note> his will and pleaſure, one part of thoſe being Children, not come to underſtanding. And upon what ground I know not, that any ſhould curtaile the Nations, which according to <hi>Gods</hi> promiſe, <hi>Abraham</hi> was to be a Father of, by cutting off one part, to wit Children, when it is ſo manifeſt a thing. Children were one part of the Iewiſh Nation, and equally intereſſed in the Covenant, and in <hi>Abraham</hi> for a Father alſo, aſwell as perſons of yeares. And that Nation when it ſhall be born againe in one day; ſhalbe compleat, and ſhall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:156525:20"/> not be a part by leaving their Children behind them. This learning the Scripture doth fully and very plentifully teach; yet ſome will conclude, as an inconveniencie fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing thereon, that if it were ſo, then there muſt needs be Nationall Churches, which followeth no more neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily from it, then tythes followeth from the Law, alledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed about the maintenance of the Miniſterie, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 14. The Inſtitution of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the one and other carryeth the force, and is to be regarded.</p>
            <p>But it may be ſayd, and is by ſome, that in the 28 <hi>Mat.</hi> 19. our Lord requireth, that they be firſt taught, and then Baptized, which Children cannot be; hereunto I ſay that this (firſt) is their owne qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in, and an addition not to be ſuffered: Nations are to be made Chriſts Diſciples by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, teaching is neceſſary before and after, concerning the knowledge of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> if perſons of yeares are firſt to be taught the knowledge of CHRIST, and then Baptiſed, it doth not follow at all, concerning Children in the leaſt, which are alwaies included in their Parents; as the proſelytes of old were to be taught the knowledge of the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> before they were received to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion the Ordinance of Initiation, but not ſo their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren: indeed it were moſt unreaſonable to require it of them, or to refuſe them becauſe of it, when nature by time hath not done its part, yet if any will inforce this ſo as b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> wringing the noſe to cauſe blood, let them teach children of 10 daies old if they pleaſe, for to refuſe them Baptiſme, they may not, for no conditionall If, may be put in their caſe, as there was none in Circumciſion of old. If any ſhall ſay, thus we learne <hi>Chriſt</hi> of <hi>Moſes,</hi> I anſwere and ſay, it is very lawfull for us ſo to do, for he wrought of him: and ſurely it is a very froward &amp; obſcure way of reaſoning, to ſet the Children, in way of opoſition to the Parents in the caſe of beleeving, &amp; of intereſt in the Covena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Almighty
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:156525:21"/> God, which the holy Scripture never doth, nor teacheth us to doe, no not by one inſtance or example: in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Nation is oppoſed and ſet in oppoſition to Nation; <hi>Iewes</hi> againſt <hi>Greeks,</hi> and other <hi>Gentiles,</hi> Families, againſt Families; and Beleevers againſt Infidells; but not Parents againſt Children, according as theſe men doe.</p>
            <p>Thus both example and precept is ſhewed in the caſe of Baptiſme of Children, which if neither could have bin ſhewed, a juſt conſequence is a reall demonſtration of the will and pleaſure of God, as in other caſes, ſo in this of Baptiſme, and that may be gathered (and is fully) in the former part of this Diſcourſe, both negatively and affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matively deduced: I leave the further conſideration of it, and the whole matter to be conſidered of by thoſe that love the truth; whom the God of truth lead into all truth for his Sonnes ſake, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
